Byzantine Institute, Inc. Dumbarton Oaks Research Library and Collection. The Byzantine Institute and Dumbarton Oaks Fieldwork Records and Papers, ca. late 1920s-2000s: Finding Aid
Image Collections and Fieldwork Archives, Dumbarton Oaks Research Library and Collection
- Fieldwork Papers, 1920s -2000s, MS.BZ.004-02; 46 boxes including 494 folders; 29 boxes including 29 photo albums; 20+ oversize files; 26 boxes of backlog materials; 2 boxes including 14 folders of accumulated research materials by ICFA staff
  - Fieldwork Reports and Drafts for Publications, 1930s-2000s, MS.BZ.004-02-02; 12 boxes containing 141 folders
    - Notes, Drafts and reports on Kariye Camii, ca. 1950s - 1960s, MS.BZ.004-02-02-05; 2 boxes including 23 folders
      - Copies of reports, fieldwork notes, and photographs, 1957, MS.BZ.004-02-02-05-406; 1 folder
        - Photographs of excavation site, 1957, MS.BZ.004-02-02-05-406-005; 11 black and white photographs
      - Notes and ground plan sketches, ca. 1950s, MS.BZ.004-02-02-05-407; 1 folder
        Includes an elevation drawing by "C.M. [Cyril Mango]," Summer 1953 and a notebook by David Oates (?), ca. 1957-1958
        David Oates was a British archaeologist who studied at Trinity College, Cambridge, and became Professor of Western Asiatic Archaeology at the University of London in 1969.
      - "INVENTORY OF ENGINEERING WORK DONE IN KARIYE UP TO OCTOBER 1960", October 29, 1960, MS.BZ.004-02-02-05-408; 1 folder
        Dimitri Zafiroglu was a Byzantine Institute field worker who conducted a survey of engineering work in Kariye Camii, ca. 1960. (Possibly later an engineer with DuPont in Delaware)
        Zafiroglu, Dimitri
        For related materials, see Subgroup 2, Series 5, Subseries 1, "Oversize: Medium," Files 553 and 555.
      - Notes and excerpts from texts about Kariye Camii, Undated, MS.BZ.004-02-02-05-409; 1 folder
      - Notes and excerpts from texts about the History of the Palaeologus Family and their monograms, Undated, MS.BZ.004-02-02-05-410; 1 folder
      - Bibliographic notes found in Loculus, Undated, MS.BZ.004-02-02-05-411; 1 folder
      - Excerpts from texts about conservation techniques, Undated, MS.BZ.004-02-02-05-412; 1 folder
      - "Elevation of Door between Diaconicon and Apse From Diaconicon, looking N", Undated, MS.BZ.004-02-02-05-413; 1 folder
      - "Theodore Metochites", Undated, MS.BZ.004-02-02-05-414; 1 folder
        B.A. Photiades was a writer, possibly affiliated with the Byzantine Institute
        Photiades, B.A.
    - Project Reports for Other Sites, ca. 1960s - 1980s, MS.BZ.004-02-02-06; 1 box including 6 folders
      - Report on the Church of the Holy Apostles (St. Peter and St. Paul) at Perachorio, Cyprus, 1959-1960, MS.BZ.004-02-02-06-415; 1 folder
      - Progress report and press release about the Episcopal Basilica at Kourion, Cyprus, ca. 1974-1976, MS.BZ.004-02-02-06-416; 1 folder
      - Progress and research reports, Evritania, Greece, 1980s, MS.BZ.004-02-02-06-417; 1 folder
        Relates to the survey of post-Byzantine monasteries, churches, and antiquities at Evritania, Greece directed by Lazaros Deriziotis and John T. A. Koumoulides in the 1980's.
        Relates to Files 418 and 419.
      - "Survey of the post-Byzantine monuments of the prefecture of Evritania, Greece: Fifth and Sixth Season", July 1985-July 1986, MS.BZ.004-02-02-06-418; 1 folder
        Relates to Files 417 and 419.
      - "Survey of the post-Byzantine Monasteries, Churches and Antiquities of the Prefecture of Evritania, Greece: Sixth Season", July 1986, MS.BZ.004-02-02-06-419; 1 folder
        Relates to Files 417 and 418.
      - Progress reports on other fieldwork projects, 1980s, MS.BZ.004-02-02-06-420; 1 folder
    - Materials and Drafts of Publication for the Kalenderhane Camii Project, ca. 1960s - 2000s, MS.BZ.004-02-02-07; 3 boxes including 20 folders
      Correspondence and Reports
      - Correspondence with Ayyüz Toydemir, ca. 1980s-2000, MS.BZ.004-02-02-07-421; 1 folder
        Relates to the publication of the Kalenderhane Camii pottery report
        Toydemir, Ayyüz
      - Correspondence between Alice-Mary Talbot and Jean-Michel Spieser, August 17, 2007, MS.BZ.004-02-02-07-422; 1 folder
        Relates to the Kalenderhane Camii publication and Ayyüz Toydemir
        Jean-Michel Spieser is a French Byzantinist, who was a senior fellow at the Center for Byzantine Studies at Dumbarton Oaks from 1997-2001
        Spieser, Jean-Michel, 1942-
      - Copy: "First Draft: Report on the Archaeological Significance of the Roman and Byzantine Pottery from Kalenderhane Camii, Istanbul", 1960s-2000, MS.BZ.004-02-02-07-423; 1 folder
        A British archaeologist and Byzantinist, Judith Herrin is Professor Emerita of Late Antique and Byzantine Studies at King's College London. She was a Dumbarton Oaks Fellow and worked at Kalendarhane Camii in Istanbul.
        Herrin, Judith, 1942-
      - Report: Copies of illustrations and table of contents for "Kalenderhane in Istanbul: Final Report on the Archaeological Exploration and Restoration, 1966-1978", 1966-1978, MS.BZ.004-02-02-07-424; 1 folder
        Doğan Kuban is a Turkish architectural historian. He represented the Department of the History of Architecture at Istanbul Technical University during restoration and investigative field work at Kalenderhane Camii in Istanbul, a joint campaign with Dumbarton Oaks, 1966 – 1974. Kuban was a Fellow at Dumbarton Oaks ca. 1960s-1970s
        Kuban, Doğan, 1926-
      - Report: Ground plans, transverse and longitudinal sections, and elevations for the Kalenderhane Camii, 1960s, MS.BZ.004-02-02-07-425; 1 folder
        Depicts the entire building, as well as the Valens aqueduct, canal, and grave plans, the north and bema churches, and the roman baths
      - Report: Copy of final draft: "Kalenderhane: Architectural Analysis and Restoration (With 44 Drawings and a Critical Catalogue of Masonry Techniques), June 1982", June 1982, MS.BZ.004-02-02-07-426; 1 folder
      - Report: Illustrations of Kalenderhane Camii ground plans, 1980s, MS.BZ.004-02-02-07-427; 1 folder
        Includes correspondence fro Kuban to Peter Topping, April 5, 1983
        Topping, Peter, 1916-2003
      - Reports: copy: "The Final Report of Kalenderhane Ceramics," pages 1-93, 1960s-2000, MS.BZ.004-02-02-07-428; 1 folder
        Ayyüz Toydemir is a historian and a former Summer Fellow at Dumbarton Oaks in 1995
        M. Hendy is an economic historian and expert on Byzantine coinage
        Hendy, M., 1942-2008
      - Reports: copy: "Ottoman Ceramic Report of Kalenderhane (To my husband Nihat), Istanbul, 1982", 1982, MS.BZ.004-02-02-07-429; 1 folder
      - Pottery report and an English translation of "Kalenderhane in the Ottoman Period", 1980s, MS.BZ.004-02-02-07-430; 1 folder
      - Pottery report (A-C): "Middle Byzantine I"; "Early Byzantine (Late Roman)"; and "Late Byzantine", 1980s, MS.BZ.004-02-02-07-431; 1 folder
      - Pottery report (D-E): "Middle Byzantine I", 1980s, MS.BZ.004-02-02-07-432; 1 folder
      - Pottery report (F-L): "Early Byzantine"; "Middle Byzantine I"; and "Middle Byzantine II", 1980s, MS.BZ.004-02-02-07-433; 1 folder
      - Pottery report (M-U): "Middle Byzantine I"; "Middle Byzantine II"; and "Early Byzantine (Late Roman)", 1980s, MS.BZ.004-02-02-07-434; 1 folder
      - "Chapter 8: Ceramics & Glass, A. Roman & Byzantine Ceramics" (Kalenderhane 1), 1980s, MS.BZ.004-02-02-07-435; 1 folder
        Title from first page: "First Draft: Report on the Archaeological Significance of the Roman and Byzantine Pottery from Kalenderhane Camii, Istanbul (Kalenderhane -1)"
      - "Chapter 8: Ceramics & Glass, A. Roman & Byzantine Ceramics" (Kalenderhane 2), 1980s, MS.BZ.004-02-02-07-436; 1 folder
        Title from first page: "The Final Report of Kalenderhane Ceramics (Kalenderhane - 2; pp. 346-614)"
      - "Chapter 8: Ceramics & Glass, A. Roman & Byzantine Ceramics" (Kalenderhane 3), 1980s, MS.BZ.004-02-02-07-437; 1 folder
        Title from first page: "The Final Report of Kalenderhane Ceramics (Kalenderhane - 3; pp. 615-949)"
      - "Chapter 9: Coins & Seals, A. Roman & Byzantine Coins (Kalenderhane - 4; pp. 950-1300)", 1980s, MS.BZ.004-02-02-07-438; 1 folder
      - "Ottoman Ceramic Report of Kalenderhane (To my husband Nihat), Istanbul, 1982" (pp. 1-150), 1982, MS.BZ.004-02-02-07-439; 1 folder
      - "Ottoman Ceramic Report of Kalenderhane (To my husband Nihat), Istanbul, 1982" (pp. 151-301), 1982, MS.BZ.004-02-02-07-440; 1 folder
  - Fieldwork Drawings and Tracings, 1930s-1960s, MS.BZ.004-02-03; 1 box including 32 folders
    Contains drawings, sketches of inscriptions, and rubbings of mason’s marks, and tracings, which were created between the 1930s and the 1960s in the Red Sea Monasteries, Egypt and Hagia Sophia and Kariye Camii, Istanbul, Turkey.
    Arranged by medium (drawings, inscriptions, rubbings, tracings, etc.) and site in sequential order.
    - Watercolor: Red Sea Monasteries, Egypt, 1930s -1960s, MS.BZ.004-02-03-01; 1 folder
      - Watercolor sketch of Saint George riding a horse, St. Anthony, Red Sea Monasteries, Egypt, 1930s - 1960s, MS.BZ.004-02-03-01-441; 1 folder
        This item (accession number: BF.F.1993.F1967) was moved from Oversize: Large (Map 2, Drawer 6, Folder 6).
    - Drawings: Hagia Sophia and Kariye Camii, Istanbul, Turkey, 1930s-1960s, MS.BZ.004-02-03-02; 16 folders of drawings
      - Hagia Sophia: Sketches of crosses located at the north and south of the soffits of the apse arch and the south window jamb, July 14, 1933, MS.BZ.004-02-03-02-442; 6 sketches
      - Hagia Sophia: Photostat of the central panel and narthex, November 9, 1934, MS.BZ.004-02-03-02-443; 1 folder
      - Hagia Sophia: "[Colour sketch of the] mosaic border below [the] figure of [Archangel in the] South [of the] Soffit Arch", June 14, 1938, MS.BZ.004-02-03-02-444; 1 folder
      - Hagia Sophia: Site map for the Deësis panel and surrounding floor plans, April 5-6, 1946, MS.BZ.004-02-03-02-445; 1 folder
      - Hagia Sophia: Site map of mosaic locations, 1930s-1960s, MS.BZ.004-02-03-02-446; 1 folder
      - Hagia Sophia: Floor plans and cutaways for the southwest corner, 1930s-1960s, MS.BZ.004-02-03-02-447; 1 folder
      - Hagia Sophia: Floor plans, 1930s-1960s, MS.BZ.004-02-03-02-448; 1 folder
      - Hagia Sophia: General plan for Southwest rooms of Hagia Sophia, 1930s-1960s, MS.BZ.004-02-03-02-449; 1 folder
      - Hagia Sophia: Unlabeled sketch book, 1930s-1960s, MS.BZ.004-02-03-02-450; 1 sketch book
        Includes drawings in charcoal and ink
      - Hagia Sophia: Notes and sketches of the Deësis panel with measurements, 1930s-1960s, MS.BZ.004-02-03-02-451; 1 folder
        Albert A. Benois was a Russian illustrator
        Benois, Albert A., 1888-
      - Hagia Sophia: Sketches of windows with measurements, 1930s-1960s, MS.BZ.004-02-03-02-452; 1 folder
      - Hagia Sophia: Sketches of the north and south tympanum wall, 1930s-1960s, MS.BZ.004-02-03-02-453; 1 folder
      - Hagia Sophia: Sketches of mosaics with a grid system, 1930s-1960s, MS.BZ.004-02-03-02-454; 1 folder
      - Kariye Camii: "MISC. DRAWINGS" with measurements, ca. late 1950s, MS.BZ.004-02-03-02-455; 1 folder
        Contains elevation drawings for Kariye Camii of the north passage, oratory, east wall, walls of the parecclesion, nave, esonarthex, exonarthex, and others
      - Kariye Camii: "ARCHITECTURAL SURVEYING OF THE CHURCH OF ST. SAVIOUR IN CHORA: EXTERIOR EAST ELEVATION", 1961, MS.BZ.004-02-03-02-456; 1 folder
        Contains elevation drawings of the parecclesion, east wall, diaconicon, minaret base, main dome, main apse, and prothesis
        Metin Ahunbay is a Turkish writer on Byzantine architecture
        Ahunbay, Metin
      - Kariye Camii: "NAOS + APSE EXCAVATIONS KARIYE CAMII", undated [1930s-1960s], MS.BZ.004-02-03-02-457; 1 folder
        Contains elevation drawings of the wall, exterior, passage, and tombs in the apse
    - Inscriptions: Hagia Sophia and Kariye Camii, Istanbul, Turkey, 1930s-1960s, MS.BZ.004-02-03-03; 7 folders of sketches
      - Hagia Sophia: Sketches of inscriptions on the ceiling, 1930s-1960s, MS.BZ.004-02-03-03-458; 1 folder
      - Hagia Sophia: Sketches of inscriptions at the northeast lunette, 1930s-1960s, MS.BZ.004-02-03-03-459; 1 folder
      - Hagia Sophia: Sketches of inscriptions at the southeast lunette, 1930s-1960s, MS.BZ.004-02-03-03-460; 1 folder
      - Hagia Sophia: Sketches of inscriptions at the southwest lunette, 1930s-1960s, MS.BZ.004-02-03-03-461; 1 folder
      - Hagia Sophia: Notes and sketches of inscriptions at the southwest gallery, 1930s-1960s, MS.BZ.004-02-03-03-462; 1 folder
      - Hagia Sophia: Sketches of inscriptions, 1930s-1960s, MS.BZ.004-02-03-03-463; 1 folder
      - Kariye Camii: Sketches of inscriptions, ca. early 1960s, MS.BZ.004-02-03-03-464; 1 folder
    - Rubbings: Hagia Sophia, Istanbul, Turkey, 1930s-1960s, MS.BZ.004-02-03-04; 7 folders of rubbings
      - Masons' marks from the west walkway (column base), 1930s-1960s, MS.BZ.004-02-03-04-465; 1 folder of rubbings
      - Masons' marks from the west walkway (division base), 1930s-1960s, MS.BZ.004-02-03-04-466; 1 folder of rubbings
      - Masons' marks from the west walkway (panel), 1930s-1960s, MS.BZ.004-02-03-04-467; 1 folder of rubbings
      - Masons' marks from the southwest gallery pavement, 1930s-1960s, MS.BZ.004-02-03-04-468; 1 folder of rubbings
        One item was removed for preservation purposes, see Subgroup 1, Series 5, Subseries 1, "Oversize: Medium" (Folder 5).
      - Masons' marks from the southwest gallery (column base), 1930s-1960s, MS.BZ.004-02-03-04-469; 1 folder of rubbings
      - Masons' marks from the southeast gallery pavement, 1930s-1960s, MS.BZ.004-02-03-04-470; 1 folder of rubbings
      - Masons' marks from an unspecified location, 1930s-1960s, MS.BZ.004-02-03-04-471; 1 folder of rubbings
    - Tracings: Hagia Sophia, Istanbul, Turkey, 1951, MS.BZ.004-02-03-05; 1 folder
      - "Rough tracing of tree design at base of aoffit at East side of window of South West Room Hagia Sophia 1951", 1951, MS.BZ.004-02-03-05-472; 1 folder
  - Audiovisual Materials, 1930s-1950s, MS.BZ.004-02-04; 32 boxes including 22 folders and 29 photoalbums
    Contains photographs, photo albums, and 16mm motion picture films. The photographs and films were produced during the fieldwork campaigns at the Red Sea Monasteries in Egypt and at Hagia Sophia, Kariye Camii, and other sites in Istanbul, Turkey from the 1930s to the 1950s. They document the fieldworkers’ conservation and restoration techniques and highlight various types of Byzantine art and architecture.
    Arranged by medium (photographs, photo albums, motion picture films, etc.) in chronological order.
    Existence and location of copies
    For digital copies of materials in this series, see the following:
    Red Sea Monasteries, Egypt (photographs) - See seven (7) compact discs: “T. Whittemore Photographic Survey of the Monastery of St. Anthony [and] St. Paul; Photographer: Kazazian.” Some photographs may also be represented in the online exhibit, "Before Byzantiium: The Early Archaeological Activities of Thomas Whittemore (1871-1931)," http://www.doaks.org/library-archives/icfa/special-projects/online-exhibitions/before-byzantium/red-sea-monasteries-gallery
    Red Sea Monasteries, Egypt (motion picture film) - http://www.doaks.org/library-archives/icfa/special-projects/moving-image-collection/red-sea-monastery-of-st-anthony
    Conservation of Mosaics at Hagia Sophia, Istanbul (photographs) - http://via.lib.harvard.edu/via/deliver/deepLinkResults?kw2=byzantine%20institute%20of%20america&kw1=hagia%20sophia&bool1=and&index2=Name&index1=Title&repositoryLimit=Dumbarton%20Oaks
    Conservation work at Hagia Sophia and Kariye Camii, Istanbul (motion picture films) - http://www.doaks.org/library-archives/icfa/special-projects/moving-image-collection
    - Original Photographs, 1929-1950s, MS.BZ.004-02-04-01; 3 boxes including 22 folders of photographs
      Includes photographs of the Red Sea Monasteries in Egypt, and Hagia Sophia, Kariye Camii, and other sites in Istanbul, as well as images of Thomas Whittemore. This series also includes oversize photographs from the same sites.
      Roughly arranged by size and then in chronological order
      For digital copies of the Red Sea Monasteries photographs, consult ICFA staff. Other copies of the Red Sea Monasteries photographs are also available in:
      Seven (7) compact discs: "T. Whittemore Photographic Survey of the Monastery of St. Anthony [and] St. Paul; Photographer: Kazazian"
      Site Book nos. 18-21
      For digital copies of Carroll Wales's photographs, see compact discs nos.: 454-469 (accession nos. 2013.0010.0865-2013.0010.0866)
      - Duplicate photographs of frescoes and watercolour copies from the Red Sea Monasteries, Egypt, 1929-1950s, MS.BZ.004-02-04-01-473; 1 folder of photographs
        Some photographs were produced by the Oxford University Press and were sent to John Thacher of the Byzantine Institute in April 1953. Watercolor copies of the frescoes at the Red Sea Monasteries were executed by Vladimir Netchetailov.
      - Duplicate photographs of St. Anthony and St. Paul, Red Sea Monasteries, Egypt, 1929-1950s, MS.BZ.004-02-04-01-474; 1 folder of photographs
        Some vintage photographs are interfiled with duplicate photographs.
        Existence and location of originals
        For related photographs, see Site Books no. 18-19.
        For digital copies of the photographs, see seven (7) compact discs: “T. Whittemore Photographic Survey of the Monastery of St. Anthony [and] St. Paul; Photographer: Kazazian.” Some photographs may also be represented in the online exhibit, "Before Byzantiium: The Early Archaeological Activities of Thomas Whittemore (1871-1931)," http://www.doaks.org/library-archives/icfa/special-projects/online-exhibitions/before-byzantium/red-sea-monasteries-gallery.
      - Vintage photographs of First Expedition at Red Sea Monasteries, Egypt, 1929-1930, MS.BZ.004-02-04-01-475; 1 folder of photographs
        Photographs annotated with titles and original negative numbers on the versos
        Kazazian served as staff photographer during the Byzantine Institute's 1930-1931 expeditions to the Red Sea Monasteries in Egypt.
        Photographs found interfiled with related negatives in ICFA cold storage in February 2012 and moved to the current collection (Accession numbers: 2012.0007.0001-.0052.
        For related photographs, see Site Books no. 18-19. Consult ICFA staff for related negatives in ICFA's cold storage (Accession numbers: 2012.0007.0001-.0052).
      - Vintage photographs of Second Expedition at Red Sea Monasteries, Egypt, 1930-1931, MS.BZ.004-02-04-01-476; 1 folder of photographs
        Photographs annotated with titles and original negative numbers on the versos. Some duplicate photographs interfiled with vintage photographs.
        Photographs found interfiled with related negatives in ICFA cold storage in February 2012 and moved to the current collection (Accession numbers: 2012.0007.0053-.0082.
        For related photographs, see Site Books no. 18-19. Consult ICFA staff for related negatives in ICFA's cold storage (Accession numbers: 2012.0007.0053-.0082).
      - Black and white photographs of watercolor copies of frescoes by Vladimir Netchetailov, Red Sea Monasteries, 1929-1950s, MS.BZ.004-02-04-01-477; 1 folder of photographs
      - Black and white photographs of Coptic lamp fragments with iconography, Red Sea Monasteries, 1929-1950s, MS.BZ.004-02-04-01-478; 1 folder of photographs
        Annotations on the versos of the photographs indicate that the lamp fragments are from the Louvre Museum in Paris and are "for paper by A. Piankoff."
      - Black and white photograph of an oil painting depicting rider saint, undated, MS.BZ.004-02-04-01-479; 1 folder with 1 photograph
        Annotation on verso: "Picture belonging to the Foreign Minister Belaten Gheta Herowy."
        Walda Sellase, Heruy, 1878-1938
      - Black and white photograph from the White Monastery in Sohag, Egypt, No Date, MS.BZ.004-02-04-01-480; 1 folder with 1 photograph
        For related photographs, see the Thomas Whittemore collection in the Coptic section of the department of Egyptian antiquities, Louvre Museum, Paris, France.
      - Black and white photographs of conservation work in Hagia Sophia, 1932-1933, MS.BZ.004-02-04-01-481; 1 folder of photographs
        Details of work in the nave, vestibule panel, and narthex
        Originally located in ICFA Administrative files.
      - Photographs of Thomas Whittemore with Edward VIII of England and Mrs. Wallis Simpson, while touring Hagia Sophia, and a newspaper clipping of Thomas Whittemore with Mustafa Kemal Atatürk, 1936, MS.BZ.004-02-04-01-482; 1 folder with photographs and newspaper clipping
        Edward VIII, 1894-1972
        Simpson, Wallis, 1896-1986
      - Photographs of Winfield Green (possibly) and color mosaic reproductions of the Madonna, Christ, and John the Baptist, 1940, MS.BZ.004-02-04-01-483; 1 folder of photographs
        Green, Winfield
      - Photographs of the central apse and soffit of the apse arch with a grid system, probably Hagia Sophia, ca. 1935-1939, MS.BZ.004-02-04-01-484; 1 folder with 3 photographs
      - Black and white photographs of conservation work in Hagia Sophia, ca. late 1930s-early 1940s, MS.BZ.004-02-04-01-485; 1 folder of photographs
        Includes photographs of: Winfield Green (possibly), 1940; George Holt and Thomas Whittemore while working on the Zoe Panel, 1938; and a fieldworker tracing John II Comnenus (John Panel)
      - Photographs of reproduction of St. John Chrysostom panel in Hagia Sophia, undated [1930s-1940s], MS.BZ.004-02-04-01-486; 1 folder with 2 color photographs
        Photographs are mounted in cardboard enclosures, each accompanied with a flysheet that indicates that the image is of a copy of the mosaic panel in Hagia Sophia, "Placed by Mrs. Crane in the Church of St. John Chrysostom in Chicago / In memory of Richard T. Crane, Jr."
        Crane, Richard Teller, Jr., 1873-1931
      - Black and white photographs including the Zoe Panel mosaics in Hagia Sophia, undated [1930s-1940s], MS.BZ.004-02-04-01-487; 1 folder of photographs
      - Contact prints of technical details, ground plans, and mosaics from Hagia Sophia, undated, MS.BZ.004-02-04-01-488; 1 folder of photographs
        Photographs found interfiled with related glass negatives in ICFA cold storage in March 2012 (Accession numbers: 2012.0014.0001-.0045) and moved to the current collection.
        Photographs printed from glass negatives that have been moved to ICFA cool storage for preservation purposes.
      - Contact prints of conservation work in Hagia Sophia, undated, MS.BZ.004-02-04-01-489; 1 folder of photographs
        Includes images of conservation tools, mosaics in the narthex, and ground plans
        Photographs found interfiled with related glass negatives in ICFA cold storage in March 2012 (Accession numbers: 2012.0012.0001-.0190) and moved to the current collection.
      - Photographic proof sheets, Kariye Camii, Istanbul, Turkey, ca. 1950s, MS.BZ.004-02-04-01-490; 1 folder with photographs mounted on sheets of paper
        Includes notes on the versos by Paul Underwood.
        For related materials, see Subgroup 2, Series 2, Subseries 5 and the Leica binder for 1958.
      - Black and white photographs of the Church of Hagia Sophia, Trabzon, Turkey, undated, MS.BZ.004-02-04-01-491; 1 folder with photographs
        Items' original title: "Trebizond: St. Sophia, from neg. by N. Kluge"; negatives possibly from Nicholas Kluge.
      - Oversize Photographs: Black and white photographs of a painting from the Red Sea Monasteries, Egypt, undated, MS.BZ.004-02-04-01-492; 1 folder of photographs